[Music]
while randomized controlled trials are
highly reliable in assessing
interventions like drugs they're harder
to do with diet
dietary diseases can take decades to
develop it's not like you can give
people placebo food and it's hard to get
people to stick to assigned diets
especially for the years it would take
to observe effects on hard endpoints
like heart disease or cancer
that's why we have to use observational
studies of large numbers of people in
their diets over time to see which foods
appear to be linked to which diseases
and interestingly if you compare data
obtained from observational population
studies versus randomized trials on
average there's little evidence for
significant differences between the
findings
not just in the same direction of effect
but of the same general magnitude of the
effect in about 90 percent of the
treatments they looked at
but wait what about the hormone
replacement therapy disparity i talked
about in the last video it turns out
when you go back and look at the data it
was just a difference in timing in terms
of when the premarine was started and
they actually showed the same results
after all but even if observational
trials did provide lower quality
evidence maybe we don't need the same
level of certainty when we're telling
someone to eat more broccoli or drink
less soda
compared to whether or not you want to
prescribe someone some drug
after all prescription drugs are the
third leading cause of death
in the united states
it goes heart disease cancer than
doctors
a hundred thousand americans wiped out
every year from the side effects of
prescription drugs taken as directed so
given the massive risks you better have
rock solid evidence that there are
benefits that outweigh the risks you're
playing with fire so darn right i want
to randomize double-blind
placebo-controlled trials for drugs but
when you're just telling people to cut
down on donuts you don't need the same
level of proof
in the end
the industry-funded sugar paper
concluding that the dietary guidelines
telling people to cut down aren't
trustworthy because they're based on
such quote unquote low quality evidence
is an example of the inappropriate use
of the drug trial paradigm in nutrition
research
you say yeah but what were the authors
supposed to do if great is the way you
judge guidelines and you can't blame
them but no there are other tools like
for example nutrigrade a scoring system
specifically designed to assess and
judge the level of evidence in nutrition
research
one of the things i like about
nutrigrade is that it specifically takes
funding bias into account so
industry-funded trials are downgraded
no wonder the industry-funded authors
chose the inappropriate drug method
instead
helm is another one hierarchies of
evidence applied to lifestyle medicine
specifically designed because existing
tools such as great are not viable
options when it comes to questions that
you can't fully address through
randomized controlled trials
in a way each research method has its
own unique contribution in a lab you can
explore the exact mechanisms rcts can
prove cause and effect and huge
population studies can study hundreds of
thousands of people at a time for
decades
take the trans fat story for example we
had randomized controlled trials showing
trans fats increased risk factors for
heart disease and we had population
studies showing that the more trans fats
people ate the more heart disease they
had and so taken together
these studies forged a strong case for
the harmful effects of trans fat
consumption on heart disease and as a
consequence it was largely removed from
the u.s food supply preventing as many
as 200 000 heart attacks every year
now it's true we never had randomized
controlled trials looking at hard end
points like heart attacks and death
because that would take years of
randomizing people to eat like canisters
of crisco every day
you can't let the perfect be the enemy
of the good when there are tens of
thousands of lives at stake
public health officials have to work
with the best available balance of
evidence there is it's like when we set
tolerable upper limits for lead exposure
or pcbs it's not like we randomized kids
to drink different levels of lead and
saw who grew up to have tolerable brain
damage you can't run those kinds of
experiments so you have to just pull in
evidence from as many sources as
possible and make your best
approximation
even if rct's randomized controlled
trials are unavailable or impossible to
conduct there's plenty of evidence from
observational studies on the nutritional
causes of many cancers such as on red
meat increasing the risk of colorectal
cancer so if dietary guidelines aiming
at cancer prevention were to be assessed
with the drug designed grade approach
they'd reached the same conclusion that
the sugar paper did low quality evidence
and so no surprise a meat industry
funded institution hired the same dude
who helped conceive and design the sugar
industry funded study and boom
lead author saying we could ignore the
dietary guidelines to reduce red and
processed meat consumption because they
used grade methods to rate the certainty
of evidence and though current dietary
guidelines recommend limiting meat
consumption their results predictably
demonstrated that the evidence was of
low quality
before i dive deep into the meat papers
one last irony about the sugar paper
the authors use the
inconsistency of the exact
recommendations across sugar guidelines
over a 20-year period to raise concerns
about the quality of the guidelines now
obviously we would expect guidelines to
evolve but the most recent guidelines
show remarkable consistency with one
exception
the 2002 institute of medicine guideline
that said a quarter of your diet could
be straight sugar without running into
deficiencies
but that outlier was partly funded by
the coke pepsi cookie candy funded
institute that is now saying see since
recommendations are all over the place
thanks in part to us
they can't be trusted
[Music]
you